Hi, my name is Jane Yee and welcome to Case by Case, a New Zealand Herald podcast brought
to you by the Open Justice team with thanks to New Zealand On Air.
Each week we take a look at a case that's making headlines and then we take a bit of
a deep dive into the justice system behind it.
And today I'm joined by Brianna McIlraith from our Open Justice team, Kia ora, Brianna.
Kia ora.
And you have a story about a rest time that was the subject of multiple complaints, it
was based in Danny Verg.
And it's really tragic, these two that we'll be talking about today, one involved a woman
who had maggots found in a wound in her leg and another woman whose breast cancer was
missed entirely.
So it really sad stories.
Tell us a little bit about this rest time.
Yeah, so the rest time at the time, so this happened between 2022 and 2024, it was called
Eileen Mary residential care and retirement village, which was operated by Eileen Mary
aged care limited.
To be clear, they no longer owned the rest home anymore, since changed hands.
So this happened between 2022 and 2024, so during that time the health and disability
commissioner received a total of four complaints relating to care provided to residents at the
rest time.
Okay, so it's not one isolated incident, there's a few things going on there with a relatively
short period of time, only a couple of years.
And these things were all investigated together, right?
Yeah, they all kind of formed one big complaint that the commissioner then investigated all
together.
Okay, so let's talk about this first complaint, which is the one where a woman was found
with maggots in her, an open wound in her leg.
Yeah, so this was a 94 year old woman who was living at the rest time.
So she was in the care facility, this was back in 2022.
And so she had a recent hospitalization for some illnesses, including heart failure.
And then she had issues with her mobility and also some wounds.
So her skin was very fragile, like dry and itchy, and then this lead to a wound that
was on her leg.
And because the rest home was in quite a rural setting, I think there was like a paddock
nearby that had sheep in it.
Which one day it was discovered that this woman's wound now had maggots in it.
So the sheep being in the paddock nearby, that lead to flies.
And is it correct that actually they were kind of, someone was aware that it was a bit
of a fly problem?
Yeah, in the decision it said a neighbour.
So I'm not sure if that means I can neighbour within the rest home or a neighbour around the
kind of rest home area.
So a neighbour kind of knew of this fly issue and was trying to mitigate it with things like
a fly spray, but ultimately that didn't help the situation as much as it really needed
to.
OK, so what did the, in terms of this case, what does the Health and Disability Commissioner
find?
Because it sounds a little bit to me like, well, no one really knew that this was going
on.
What are the steps that should have been in place to prevent this from happening?
Yeah, so basically there was just inadequate care overall, a lack of communication between
teams within the rest home, a lack of like wound management care.
Surely they'll be checking on this one.
Yeah.
And I think at the time now, like you need to take photos of wounds that you're kind of
caring for as a nurse or a doctor, but at the time this wasn't in place or it was poorly
managed by the rest home.
So things were kind of getting missed along the way to the point where it got really serious
for this woman.
So the complaint was upheld?
Yes, yes.
OK.
And then complaint too, when we're talking about things being missed, it was alleged that
they missed this woman's entire breast cancer.
Yeah, so this woman had an inter-dictional disability, which meant that for the most part
she was non-verbal, she only could kind of communicate through like yelling and things
like that.
So she was getting her pain managed, so if she was in pain she could just yell out.
But it wasn't being properly cared for, she wasn't being listened to properly.
And yeah, it was discovered that she had breast cancer that had gone quite advanced by the
time that it was picked up outside of the rest home.
So they kind of noticed something was wrong with her breast that then got escalated to kind
of like hospital level care who ultimately said like it's just too advanced.
When you're talking about this woman yelling out for pain relief, what sort of pain relief
was she getting?
They were kind of just giving her the usual like paracetamol, like what you would kind
of usually prescribe for pain because they couldn't tell how advanced this kind of pain
she was actually feeling with her being non-verbal.
But it was also noted by staff that she was becoming increasingly like agitated, but it
wasn't really picked up on that this could be related to pain.
Right.
What did the what did the commissioner say in contents of all of this?
Basically the commissioner said that it was found that there was actually history of breast
cancer within the woman's family, but the rest home failed to look at the family history
of this woman.
So the lack of communication and I guess like filekeeping was called out in that respect.
I find this kind of escalation of her communicating pain seems like something that they'd pick
up on too.
Because paracetamol is a great pain relief, but presumably if you have cancer, there's
a great deal of pain because it was quite advanced, wasn't it?
Yeah.
So they basically said there was also a lack of timely recognition in her advanced pain
and also like the changes to her breast.
So there was a lack of recognition there.
The woman unfortunately also passed away because of the breast cancer and the commissioner
was quite critical of the end of life care that the rest home provided as well.
So just a lack of management of end of life care and giving her comfort as well.
Do we know who made the complaints in these two cases?
Yeah.
In regards to the first complaint, it was the son of the woman and then for the second complaint
it was actually referred to HTC by the coroner.
I've got two pretty serious complaints here and they were two of four.
What can you tell me about the other complaints that were investigated with these ones?
Yeah.
So the other two were also related to wound management issues within the facility.
One was so bad that the failures in care lead to the person getting sepsis in an ambulance
was ultimately called.
There was also no access to the facility, the retirement facility for the ambulance.
So they were actually left waiting for 30 minutes outside of the facility.
This is the ambulance trying to get in to the rest time.
Yeah.
Okay.
So they was out there for 30 minutes which obviously delayed care to the patient and then
later on she died of sepsis.
All four were upheld.
Okay.
Were there any recommendations made by the commissioner in this investigation?
Yeah.
So the commissioner recognised that the wound care plans were not up to scratch.
There was poor communication between practitioners regarding these cases.
So it's requested that there was an apology made to all four families regarding each case
and then also kind of doing audits on patients and their care and the management plan and also
going back to the commissioner with the steps that they've taken to remedy these situations
and make sure that they've learned from them.
But as you said earlier, the rest time is actually now under new management.
Have they taken on board the recommendations?
Yeah.
So the recommendations have been taken on by the original rest time and the new rest
time kind of.
Okay.
So before it changed hands, they'd taken on board the recommendations, implemented change
and that's now floated to the new owners also.
Thanks Brianna.
We're going to take a wee break and then when we come back, we'll be talking more about
the Health and Disability Commissioner, what it's there for because rest home complaints
are just one part of what it deals with, these plenty more that it covers.
So we'll be back to discuss just after this.
I'm Jamie and you're with case by case from the New Zealand Herald's Open Justice team
with thanks to New Zealand On Air.
Now, most of us hope we will never need the Health and Disability Commissioner.
But if something goes wrong with your health care, it's good to know what it can and can't
do.
And joining me now to find out what it can and can't do is Brianna McIlraith from the open
justice team, Kia ora, Brianna.
So first of all, the Health and Disability Commissioner, is it a person?
Is it an entity?
What is it?
Yeah, it's an independent commissioner who has several other people to help investigate
complaints regarding health care.
So technically the commissioner is one person, but it sort of speaks on others who work on
her behalf also.
Yeah.
Okay.
And what's the purpose of the commissioner?
So everybody using a health or disability service have rights.
So there's a code of rights and it's there to promote these rights and also protect consumers
to make sure everyone is treated fairly and correctly when using health services.
So what sort of practices and services does the HDC, as we'll pull it from here, what
does, what does they have oversight over?
A whole bunch.
So you've got through to like age, residential care, to hospitals, to dentists, dental assistants,
pharmacists.
So a whole huge umbrella of people under health services.
So it can be organisations, it can be individual practitioners, does it include like naturopaths
and sort of alternative, you know, practitioners?
Yeah.
And what about councillors?
I'm guessing, because disability is in the name of the Health and Disability Commissioner
disability services.
Yeah.
So anything basically that's to do with health care and you're right.
Okay.
Gotcha.
That's a huge number of different professions and organisations, presumably there's also
a huge array of complaints that come across the HDC's desk as well.
What are some that you can think of?
So things like ambulances not arriving on time and home care is not turning up for work.
To care for someone, pharmacists, mucking up prescriptions, all sorts of things.
So x-rays, right?
I'm just like as I'm sitting here thinking all the things, midwives, you know, looking
after home births that could go wrong or even in a hospital, misdiagnosis, inappropriate
behaviour in a consultation, you know, perhaps not even taking their like when you go and
get a message and they give you a form to fill out, perhaps not giving you a form to
fill out.
That would all fall under what the HDC has oversight on.
Yeah.
And basically you're right as a patient.
Right.
So what are your rights as a patient?
Yeah.
So there's 10 rights in the code of rights.
So just to sum up, it's like you need to have dignity when you're receiving your health
care.
You need to be fully informed about your care, so strong communication skills and that you
can give consent and you have given consent for your treatment.
So there's a bunch of things that you are kind of protected as like also kind of like
a consumer of receiving this health care.
And all of those I'm assuming are on the Health and Disability Commission website so you can go
and have a look at those.
How many complaints does the HDC see in say a year?
Yeah.
So on average, it's about almost 3,500 complaints that they're receiving but they don't investigate
all of them.
So only about 180 actually investigated every year or like meet the threshold to be investigated.
So if they aren't investigated, it could just be passed back to the provider, the service
and they may be able to sort it out.
But then out of those 180 there are investigated about 75% of those are held for breaching code
of rights.
Okay.
Cool.
And so then also you've got, as you mentioned, things being punted back to the providers
or the practitioners to perhaps sort out the income to some sort of agreement with the
complainant.
What about the things that the HDC doesn't look at?
We've talked a bit about some of the complaints that may come across the desk but what are
the sorts of things that do not fall under the agreement?
Yeah.
So there's things like ACC decisions that don't, they don't investigate health privacy information
so that would be necessary to go to like the privacy commissioner, like fees charged
for your services.
Like we all know going to get a service, especially in health care is pretty expensive but they
don't look at things like fees and what you've kind of charged.
Also like your medical files being submitted to court or other people in the justice system,
that's all like kind of through privacy.
Okay.
And so what's the medical council?
Because I've heard of the medical council, what is that in relation to the health and
disability commissioner?
So the medical council of New Zealand is a professional like regulatory body that registers
your doctors, your health practitioners and kind of sets the clinical incompetence standards
that health practitioners must follow.
Okay.
With the HDC, what sort of powers do they have?
They've done an investigation and they have found that someone or an organisation has
breached that code.
What happens then?
So a lot of the time they will make the service or practitioner apologise to the family or
the person that's made the complaint or has been affected by the health service like wrongdoing.
So there's always an apology.
They can also recommend changes that a practitioner or a health service must make and a lot of
the time they must come back to them within a certain amount of time to say like three
months since the decision was released to say like, yeah, we've made these changes.
This is what we've done.
This is how it's working so that the health care improves and the kind of same thing
doesn't happen again.
Okay.
So there's a bit of a follow-up as well to make sure things are being enacted.
What is the process if you have a complaint?
Do you have to go to your provider first or can you bypass them and go straight to the
commissioner?
It is recommended that you always start with the provider of the service to make the complaint
and see what you can kind of work with.
Then if that doesn't work out or you think that that's not going to get you anywhere,
you can go straight to the HTC.
Okay.
Awesome.
Hey, thank you, Brianna.
There's actually the HTC website has got loads of valuable information.
So if you want to learn more, perhaps you want to lodge a complaint, you can just go
there.
That's the Health and Disability Commission website.
Thanks, Brianna.
Thanks for joining us and sharing your insight.
That's been case by case from the Open Justice team here at the New Zealand Herald.
Thanks to New Zealand On Air.